{"ipcData":0.97461,"initial-test-data":{"test-number":1,"is-test-active":false,"cards":[{"question":"Compare the processes by which state power shifted in various parts of Africa from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"The British used both diplomacy and warfare to expand their empire in Africa, causing state power to shift.\n\nFor example, in 1873, Britain signed a treaty with the Kingdom of Opobo in present-day Nigeria, recognizing King Jaja as the ruler and creating fair trading terms with them. This gave the Kingdom of Opobo some power as well as allowing the British to gain resources that could help them expand their empire.\n\nHowever, there are many examples where the British simply used their superior military to consolidate power. For example, the Yaa Asantewaa War was the final stand against the British trying to take over the Asante Empire in present-day Ghana, West Africa. It ended with a British victory in 1900. Yaa Asantewaa, the warrior queen that led the war, was exiled and the Asante Empire became a part of the Gold Coast colony, shifting more state power into the hands of the British.\n\nAnother example of British warfare shifting state power was when the British took control of the Dutch Cape Colony in South Africa. As a result of the takeover, tensions between Dutch Afrikaners and the British rose, leading to the Boer Wars wherein the Dutch Afrikaners fought with the British over the land in South Africa. Eventually, the British won and put the Dutch Afrikaners and South Africans in concentration camps. ","group":0},{"question":"Explain and provide a historical example of how the desire to religiously convert indigenous populations contributed to the development of imperialism from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"The desire to religiously convert indigenous populations contributed to the development of imperialism from 1750 to 1900 by justifying imperialism as the means to fulfill the Christian mission of bringing others into the fold of Christianity and the Christian mission of humanitarian aid. \n\nBritish Protestant missionaries in the 18th and 19th centuries attempted to convert colonized peoples to Christianity because they believed that Christianity was the truth. These people also set up schools, provided medical care, and tried to end the illegal slave trade.","group":0},{"question":"Explain and provide examples of the ethnic and racial prejudice faced by Chinese immigrants.","answer":"As more and more of the Chinese emigrated to the U.S and Australia and ethnic enclaves began to form in these areas, they competed with white Americans and Europeans for jobs. Furthermore, as the Chinese immigrants were willing to work for less, they were usually able to get hired more often. This created a resentment amongst white Americans and Europeans for Chinese immigrants, fostering racism and institutionalized discrimination.\n\nThe Chinese Exclusion Act of 1882 was implemented to ban further Chinese immigration to the U.S.\n\nThe Californian consitution of 1879 did not allow Chinese workers to become citizens and banned Chinese workers from being hired by the government.\n\nAfter several regulation and restriction acts by the British against Chinese immigrants, the White Australia Policy was implemented in order to preserve a \"white Australia.\"","group":0},{"question":"Explain and provide historical examples of how environmental and economic factors contributed to the development of varied patterns of migration from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"Environmental and economic factors contributed to the development of varied patterns of migration from 1750 to 1900 by making migration the preferrable option for many people or by being forced into it for others. \n\nFor example, many British geologists and engineers, Italians, Japanese, Chinese, and Irish workers freely migrated to urban cities in regions like South Africa, Argentina, the Pacific, and the U.S because of \n1) financial/job opportunities (pull factors)\n2) and environmental/demographic push factors (Irish Potato Famine, Chinese famine, politics like Taiping Rebellion).\n\nIt is important to note that this significantly increased urbanization in the 19th century as more and more people moved to cities. It is also important to know that new modes of transportation enabled immigrants to periodically or permanently move back to their home countries.\n\nHowever, the global capitalist system still relied on coerced and semicoerced labor migration as well as convict labor. For example, Chinese and Indian unskilled workers were often made indentured servants through contracts. One example of that is when South Asian workers signed low-wage, indentured servitude contracts after they lost their jobs due to an influx of cheap British cotton. Convicts, on the other hand, were sent to penal colonies wherein they were forced to do harsh labor under tough conditions. After serving their terms, most stayed in their colonies as transportation costs were too high to go back home. (Australia was once a British penal colony and the French had one in French Guiana)\n","group":0},{"question":"Explain how and why new patterns of migration affected gender roles from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"As migrants to urban areas tended to be male, many women who no longer had a male head-of-the-house became more autonomous and authoritative and began to take on more traditionally-male responsiblities. This trend occured because as men emigrated, they left traditonally-male responsiblities that women, without another male head-of-the-house, were the only ones who could take them up.\n\nIf a woman reunited with their husband either by themselves emigrating or their husbands immigrating, they would usually continue to exercise more decision-making power.","group":0},{"question":"Explain how economic imperialism is situated within the broader historical context.","answer":"The Industrial Revolution developed the demand for raw materials, which led to American and European merchants and companies trying to exert their influence on other territories to gain these resources. Furthermore, the Industrial Revolution also developed the ability for the U.S and Europe to control other territories through steamships, railroads, and military weapons, allowing American and European merchants to continue exerting influence on other territories in order to gain more resources regardless of how those territories reacted.","group":0},{"question":"Explain how trade in Latin America was organized in a way that gave merchants and companies based in Europe and the U.S a distinct economic advantage from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"European and American merchants and companies heavily invested in and exerted their economic influence over Latin American countries in order to funnel natural resources as efficiently and cheaply as possible into Europe and America. These merchants and companies did this by turning these areas in Latin America into export economies that relied on European and American investments to function (remember mining in Chile or farming in Argentina) or that were forced into being export economies through the use of government intervention (remember banana republics in Central America and the Caribbean).","group":0},{"question":"Explain how various economic factors contributed to the development of the Chinese economy from 1750 to 1900. ","answer":"1) Chinese luxury goods were in high demand in Europe; however, British goods were not in high demand in China.\n2) There was only one port in which foreign countries could trade at.\n3) British silver reserves had fallen due to Europeans using British silver to buy luxury goods.\n\nThe British East India Company noticed that British-controlled India was suitable for the growth of opium, so the company forced Indians to farm opium and then sold said opium in China for Chinese silver and then used said silver to buy Chinese luxury goods and then sold said goods to Europeans for profit. \n\nThe Chinese government did not want, however, their country to be harmed by the sale of opium, so they sent messages back to Britain, hoping that they would ban the sale of opium to China. However, Britian did not heed, leading to the Opium wars in which the Chinese fought against the British and, at times, the French. Eventually, China lost the wars, forcing them to sign the Treaty of Nanking and the Treaty of Tientsin.\n\nThe treaties and later economic imperialism by other countries, such as the U.S and Japan, forced the Chinese to\n1) open several new ports for foreign countries to trade at \n2) give Britain the island of Hong Kong\n3) legalize opium\n4) and give other countries exclusive trading rights in China. \n\nThus, Britain and other countries exerted their influence over China's economy.","group":0},{"question":"Explain how various environmental factors contributed to the development of the global economy from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"Environmental factors contibuted to the development of the global economy from 1750 to 1900 by providing the means for a country to become an export economy. For instance, after Egypt gained full control of itself, Egypt was already centered around the exportation of cotton. Instead of changing that, the Egytian people continued to primarily export cotton as Egypt was an ideal place to grow it and European countries would pay for it. Due to the environmental factor of Egypt being an ideal place to grow cotton, its economy became dependent on that cash crop. Likewise, many other country's economies' became dependent on a natural resource that was abundant or ideal to farm in said country.","group":0},{"question":"Explain the history of the VOC and the shift of its power to the Dutch government.","answer":"The Dutch East India Company, a.k.a VOC, was a private Dutch company that took control of the Spice Islands (modern-day Indonesia) because spices like nutmeg and cloves were in high demand in Europe. Eventually, however, the company went bankrupt due to heavy corruption, and the Dutch government took control of the land. The Dutch government set up plantations and farmed cash crops, leading to critiscisms from the people. The Dutch then instituted humanitarian reforms. ","group":0},{"question":"Explain the process by which state power shifted in the Congo Free State from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"State power shifted in the Congo Free State in 1908 through the international community pressuring King Leopold II to give the Congo Free State over to the country of Belgium because of the extreme human rights abuses. This historical development occured after King Leopold II of Belgium invaded and took ownership of the Congo in Central Africa and installed a ruthless system of abusive slavery in the nation in order to accumulate wealth. In fact, eight million congolese people died under his reign. ","group":0}]},"activeSets":{"view":{"category":"AP World History","title":"Unit 6"},"edit":{"category":null,"title":null},"study":{"category":"History","title":"1750 to 1900"}},"study-data":{"AP World History":{"Unit 6":{"description":"History that covers the world!","type-of-deck":"Normal","date-of-start":"04/13/2023 15:39:36","alloted_days":"100","days-of-study":{"monday":false,"tuesday":false,"wednesday":true,"thursday":false,"friday":false,"saturday":true,"sunday":false},"expected-end-state":0.97461,"memory":{"a":null,"b":null,"S":[]},"cards":[{"question":"Compare the processes by which state power shifted in various parts of Africa from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"The British used both diplomacy and warfare to expand their empire in Africa, causing state power to shift.\n\nFor example, in 1873, Britain signed a treaty with the Kingdom of Opobo in present-day Nigeria, recognizing King Jaja as the ruler and creating fair trading terms with them. This gave the Kingdom of Opobo some power as well as allowing the British to gain resources that could help them expand their empire.\n\nHowever, there are many examples where the British simply used their superior military to consolidate power. For example, the Yaa Asantewaa War was the final stand against the British trying to take over the Asante Empire in present-day Ghana, West Africa. It ended with a British victory in 1900. Yaa Asantewaa, the warrior queen that led the war, was exiled and the Asante Empire became a part of the Gold Coast colony, shifting more state power into the hands of the British.\n\nAnother example of British warfare shifting state power was when the British took control of the Dutch Cape Colony in South Africa. As a result of the takeover, tensions between Dutch Afrikaners and the British rose, leading to the Boer Wars wherein the Dutch Afrikaners fought with the British over the land in South Africa. Eventually, the British won and put the Dutch Afrikaners and South Africans in concentration camps. ","group":0},{"question":"Explain and provide a historical example of how the desire to religiously convert indigenous populations contributed to the development of imperialism from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"The desire to religiously convert indigenous populations contributed to the development of imperialism from 1750 to 1900 by justifying imperialism as the means to fulfill the Christian mission of bringing others into the fold of Christianity and the Christian mission of humanitarian aid. \n\nBritish Protestant missionaries in the 18th and 19th centuries attempted to convert colonized peoples to Christianity because they believed that Christianity was the truth. These people also set up schools, provided medical care, and tried to end the illegal slave trade.","group":0},{"question":"Explain and provide examples of the ethnic and racial prejudice faced by Chinese immigrants.","answer":"As more and more of the Chinese emigrated to the U.S and Australia and ethnic enclaves began to form in these areas, they competed with white Americans and Europeans for jobs. Furthermore, as the Chinese immigrants were willing to work for less, they were usually able to get hired more often. This created a resentment amongst white Americans and Europeans for Chinese immigrants, fostering racism and institutionalized discrimination.\n\nThe Chinese Exclusion Act of 1882 was implemented to ban further Chinese immigration to the U.S.\n\nThe Californian consitution of 1879 did not allow Chinese workers to become citizens and banned Chinese workers from being hired by the government.\n\nAfter several regulation and restriction acts by the British against Chinese immigrants, the White Australia Policy was implemented in order to preserve a \"white Australia.\"","group":0},{"question":"Explain and provide historical examples of how environmental and economic factors contributed to the development of varied patterns of migration from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"Environmental and economic factors contributed to the development of varied patterns of migration from 1750 to 1900 by making migration the preferrable option for many people or by being forced into it for others. \n\nFor example, many British geologists and engineers, Italians, Japanese, Chinese, and Irish workers freely migrated to urban cities in regions like South Africa, Argentina, the Pacific, and the U.S because of \n1) financial/job opportunities (pull factors)\n2) and environmental/demographic push factors (Irish Potato Famine, Chinese famine, politics like Taiping Rebellion).\n\nIt is important to note that this significantly increased urbanization in the 19th century as more and more people moved to cities. It is also important to know that new modes of transportation enabled immigrants to periodically or permanently move back to their home countries.\n\nHowever, the global capitalist system still relied on coerced and semicoerced labor migration as well as convict labor. For example, Chinese and Indian unskilled workers were often made indentured servants through contracts. One example of that is when South Asian workers signed low-wage, indentured servitude contracts after they lost their jobs due to an influx of cheap British cotton. Convicts, on the other hand, were sent to penal colonies wherein they were forced to do harsh labor under tough conditions. After serving their terms, most stayed in their colonies as transportation costs were too high to go back home. (Australia was once a British penal colony and the French had one in French Guiana)\n","group":0},{"question":"Explain how and why new patterns of migration affected gender roles from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"As migrants to urban areas tended to be male, many women who no longer had a male head-of-the-house became more autonomous and authoritative and began to take on more traditionally-male responsiblities. This trend occured because as men emigrated, they left traditonally-male responsiblities that women, without another male head-of-the-house, were the only ones who could take them up.\n\nIf a woman reunited with their husband either by themselves emigrating or their husbands immigrating, they would usually continue to exercise more decision-making power.","group":0},{"question":"Explain how economic imperialism is situated within the broader historical context.","answer":"The Industrial Revolution developed the demand for raw materials, which led to American and European merchants and companies trying to exert their influence on other territories to gain these resources. Furthermore, the Industrial Revolution also developed the ability for the U.S and Europe to control other territories through steamships, railroads, and military weapons, allowing American and European merchants to continue exerting influence on other territories in order to gain more resources regardless of how those territories reacted.","group":0},{"question":"Explain how trade in Latin America was organized in a way that gave merchants and companies based in Europe and the U.S a distinct economic advantage from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"European and American merchants and companies heavily invested in and exerted their economic influence over Latin American countries in order to funnel natural resources as efficiently and cheaply as possible into Europe and America. These merchants and companies did this by turning these areas in Latin America into export economies that relied on European and American investments to function (remember mining in Chile or farming in Argentina) or that were forced into being export economies through the use of government intervention (remember banana republics in Central America and the Caribbean).","group":0},{"question":"Explain how various economic factors contributed to the development of the Chinese economy from 1750 to 1900. ","answer":"1) Chinese luxury goods were in high demand in Europe; however, British goods were not in high demand in China.\n2) There was only one port in which foreign countries could trade at.\n3) British silver reserves had fallen due to Europeans using British silver to buy luxury goods.\n\nThe British East India Company noticed that British-controlled India was suitable for the growth of opium, so the company forced Indians to farm opium and then sold said opium in China for Chinese silver and then used said silver to buy Chinese luxury goods and then sold said goods to Europeans for profit. \n\nThe Chinese government did not want, however, their country to be harmed by the sale of opium, so they sent messages back to Britain, hoping that they would ban the sale of opium to China. However, Britian did not heed, leading to the Opium wars in which the Chinese fought against the British and, at times, the French. Eventually, China lost the wars, forcing them to sign the Treaty of Nanking and the Treaty of Tientsin.\n\nThe treaties and later economic imperialism by other countries, such as the U.S and Japan, forced the Chinese to\n1) open several new ports for foreign countries to trade at \n2) give Britain the island of Hong Kong\n3) legalize opium\n4) and give other countries exclusive trading rights in China. \n\nThus, Britain and other countries exerted their influence over China's economy.","group":0},{"question":"Explain how various environmental factors contributed to the development of the global economy from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"Environmental factors contibuted to the development of the global economy from 1750 to 1900 by providing the means for a country to become an export economy. For instance, after Egypt gained full control of itself, Egypt was already centered around the exportation of cotton. Instead of changing that, the Egytian people continued to primarily export cotton as Egypt was an ideal place to grow it and European countries would pay for it. Due to the environmental factor of Egypt being an ideal place to grow cotton, its economy became dependent on that cash crop. Likewise, many other country's economies' became dependent on a natural resource that was abundant or ideal to farm in said country.","group":0},{"question":"Explain the history of the VOC and the shift of its power to the Dutch government.","answer":"The Dutch East India Company, a.k.a VOC, was a private Dutch company that took control of the Spice Islands (modern-day Indonesia) because spices like nutmeg and cloves were in high demand in Europe. Eventually, however, the company went bankrupt due to heavy corruption, and the Dutch government took control of the land. The Dutch government set up plantations and farmed cash crops, leading to critiscisms from the people. The Dutch then instituted humanitarian reforms. ","group":0},{"question":"Explain the process by which state power shifted in the Congo Free State from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"State power shifted in the Congo Free State in 1908 through the international community pressuring King Leopold II to give the Congo Free State over to the country of Belgium because of the extreme human rights abuses. This historical development occured after King Leopold II of Belgium invaded and took ownership of the Congo in Central Africa and installed a ruthless system of abusive slavery in the nation in order to accumulate wealth. In fact, eight million congolese people died under his reign. ","group":0}]}},"History":{"1750 to 1900":{"description":"","type-of-deck":"Crunch","date-of-start":"04/13/2023 13:34:14","alloted_days":null,"days-of-study":{"monday":false,"tuesday":false,"wednesday":false,"thursday":false,"friday":false,"saturday":false,"sunday":false},"expected-end-state":null,"memory":{"a":null,"b":null,"S":[]},"cards":[{"question":"How did Britain handle the rights of the Australian Aboriginals and the Maori people in New Zealand?","answer":"Although the British government told British settlers in Australia to treat the Aboriginals kindly, the settlers killed the Aboriginals trying to protect their territory and resources.\n\nAs for the Maori people, Britain promised them in the Treaty of Waitangi of 1840 that the British will not infringe on their property. However, the British still infringed on the Maori people's property rights, leading to the Maori wars. Conflict and tension continued between the Maori people and the British, but, eventually, the Maori people lost most of their land by 1900.","group":0},{"question":"How did the Philipphine Revolution begin? What happened to the Philipphines after it won against the Spanish?","answer":"The Phllippine Revolution began after the Spanish government executed Jose Rizal, a Filipino that had successfully conducted a reform movement called Liga Filipina in order to educate the Filipino people. Many now-educated Filipinos were shocked at the execution, so with their growing nationalism, several revolts around the region were carried out. With American intervention, the Filippino's defeated the Spanish.\n\nHowever, after the war was over, the Americans took control of the Philippines. This led to the Philippine-American War, which would end in a U.S victory in 1902 after more than 200 thousand Filipinos died.","group":0},{"question":"What are some important natural resources? Which economy exported them?","answer":"Cotton - It was used to make textiles. Egypt exported it.\n\nRubber - It was used for tires, gaskets, hoses, etc. Areas in the Amazon and the Congo Basin exported it.\n\nPalm Oil - It was used to lubricate machinery in factories. West Africa exported it.\n\nGuano - It was an excellent fertilizer. Chile and Peru exported it.\n\nMeat - It was a foodstuff. Argentina and Uruguay exported it.\n\nDiamonds - They were prized possessions. The De Beers Mining Company, based in South Africa, accounted for 90% of all diamond production. The head of the company, Cecil Rhodes, became prime minister of the Cape Colony in 1890.","group":0},{"question":"What are some internal problems that China was going through?","answer":"China underwent many major internal problems between the period of 1750 to 1900:\n\nFailed civil servant Hong Xiuquan, starving peasents, workers, and miners attempted to overthrow the Qing Dynasty in the Taiping Rebellion. During the Taiping Rebellion, the Yellow River (Huang He) changed course, flooding farmlands and leaving other areas without water. This caused massive famine and drought. Furthermore, the bubonic plague broke out, killing many. After more than 20 million deaths, the Taiping Rebellion eventually ended with a Qing victory with the help of Chinese warlords and French and British support. \n\nThe Boxer Rebelion, supported by Empress Cixi, was ordered to kill foreigners on Chinese land. However, the Boxers mostly killed Chinese Christians, humiliating the Chinese government.\n\n","group":0},{"question":"What European imperialistic behavior took place in Egypt?","answer":"A French company managed 1.5 million (largely-unpaid) Egyptian workers to build the Suez Canal, an extremely significant waterway that could save a trip around the entire African continent to Asia. It was completed in 1869 after thousands had died in the process. The British took control of Egypt in 1882 to protect their commercial interests and to continue operating the Suez Canal on their own terms.","group":0},{"question":"What is a settler colony? What is a historical example of one?","answer":"A settler colony is a colony in which a large part of the colonizing nation's people settle in the colony.\n\n1) Originally an Ottoman territory, Algeria became a French settler colony, where Spanish, Italian, and French immigrants lived.\n2) New Zealand was also a settler colony where British immigrants lived.","group":0},{"question":"What is an economic motive for European Imperialism? What is a historical example of this?","answer":"Due to the increased need for resources as a result of the Industrial Revolution, Europeans began to colonize other nations. In order to maximize profits, the methods of slavery and the use of the military were introduced, leading to the increase in European wealth and power.\n\nThe British East India Company first went into India to trade. However, they soon held a military-backed monopoly on the Indian subcontinent. In 1858, after the British EIC had colonized parts of India, the British government dissolved the company and took control of the colonized parts of India. The British government then colonized the entire subcontinent.","group":0},{"question":"What is Nationalism? Explain how it contributed to the development of imperialism from 1750 to 1900. What is a historical example of this?","answer":"Nationalism is the loyalty and pride in one's nation.\n\nNationalism contributed to the development of imperialism from 1750 to 1900 by justifying imperialism. It did this through the idea that since was \"obviously\" superior and more deserving of wealth and power than other nations, it was okay to impose culture, religion, rule, and so on over other nations. \n\nJapan used its nationalist pride as a justification for incursions in Korea, which China held more presence in. This led to the Sino-Japanese war between Japan and China. Japan won the war and took control of Korea and Formosa (Taiwan). ","group":0},{"question":"What is Scientific Racism? What is one example of Scientific Racism? How was it used to justify European imperialism?","answer":"Scientific Racism was the means to justify the psuedoscientific idea that white Europeans were biologically superior to other races. \n\nSome phrenologists thought that a smaller skull size meant that one was worse off mentally. This was used against Africans, indigenous populations, and Asians as a proof of intellectual inferiority.\n\nScientific Racism was used to justify European imperialism by illustrating that nonwhite peoples were intellectually and physically inferior to white people and that, therefore, white people are and should be the dominant, ruling population.","group":0},{"question":"What is the Berlin Conference? How did the Berlin Conference lead to widespread war in 20th-century Africa?","answer":"The Berlin Conference was the meeting of many European nations to decide who owned what territories in Africa. It was held by Germany in order to maintain the peace as European competition for African lands threatened war amongst European nations. \n\nBecause European nations had littled regard as to which peoples they grouped into one nation, some rival groups were \"united\" while other unified groups were separated. After Europeans withdrew themselves from these African lands, rival groups fought each other for control over their respective nations, leading to widespread war.","group":0},{"question":"What is the concept of the \"civilizing mission\"? Explain how it contributed to the development of imperialism from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"The \"civilizing mission\" is the idea that because other nations/peoples were supposedly underdeveloped or backwards technologically, culturally, education-wise, government-wise, and so on, the nations' with supposed progress can and should colonize those areas in order to help them in those aspects.\n\nThe concept of the \"civilizing mission\" contributed to the development of imperialism from 1750 to 1900 by justifying imperialism by indicating that the colonization was for the supposed betterment and progress of the colonized. ","group":0},{"question":"What is the definition of Social Darwinism? Explain how it contributed to the development of imperialism from 1750 to 1900.","answer":"Social Darwinism, an interpretation of Darwinism, is the idea that a biologically-superior people, the people with the most wealth and power, is the product of conflict and competition amongst many different peoples.\n\nSocial Darwinism contributed to the development of imperialism from 1750 to 1900 by justifying European imperialism by shifting the blame of imperialistic behaviors onto evolution and how nature itself is unfair.","group":0},{"question":"What is the Ghost Dance?","answer":"Influenced by religious ideas, the Ghost Dance was a set of ritual dances and songs that were done in order to hasten the supposed event in which the dead would rise and drive out the Americans who had stolen the land of the Natives. The dance was a part of the Native American resistance movement against the Americans trying to take their land.","group":0}]}}},"tracker-data":[{"title":"Untitled","subtitle":"Due in 0 day(s)."},{"title":"Untitled","subtitle":"Due in 0 day(s)."},{"title":"Untitled","subtitle":"Due in 0 day(s)."}],"timers-data":[],"notes-data":[{"category-name":"Tomtato","items":{}}]}